作为第一个例子，我们看一个非常简单的
使用分组密码加密的方法
So as our first example let's look at a
very simple way of using a block cipher
特别地，我们将看到如何使用一次性密钥的分组密码
for encryption. In particular we'll see
how to use a block cipher with a one time
那么在本节，我们将使用分组密码来加密
key. So in this segment we're just gonna
use the block cipher to encrypt using keys
并使用一次性的密钥。换句话说
所有的攻击者能看到的都是密文
that are used one time. In other words,
all the adversary gets to see is one ciphertext,
它的目标是破坏密文的语义安全
and its goal is to break semantic
security of that ciphertext. Now, in the
在下一节里，我们要面对更有趣的分组密码的应用
next segment, we're going to turn into
more, interesting applications of block
我们要看，如何用多次使用的密钥
ciphers and we're going to see how to
encrypt using keys that are used many,
加密大量的信息。那么在我们开始前，我想说
many times to encrypt many messages. So
before we start, I want to mention that
使用分组密码时有一经典错误
there's like a classic mistake in using a
block cipher. Unfortunately, there are some
很不幸，有一些产品犯了这个错误
因此被完全破解了
products that actually work this way, and
they are badly broken, so I want to make
所以我想确保大家不要再犯这个错误
sure that none of you guys actually make
this mistake. So this mode of operation is
这个操作模式叫做电子密码本，如下工作：
called an electronic code book. And it
works as follows: it's the first thing
它是使用分组密码加密时，第一个产生的想法
that comes to mind when you want to use a
block cipher for encryption. What we do is
去我们的明文信息，将其分成若干分组
每个分组大小与密码分组大小一样
we take our message, we break it into
blocks, each block as big as the block's
在AES中，我们会把我们的明文信息分成
cipher block. So in the case of AES, we
would be breaking our message into sixteen
16个字节一个分组。然后我们将每个分组单独加密
byte blocks. And then we encrypt each
block separately. So this mode is often
所以这种模式经常叫做电子密码本
很不幸，这是极不安全的
called electronic codebook. And,
unfortunately, it's terribly insecure
因为大家发现，如果两个分组一样
比如这里，这两个分组正好一样
because you realize if two blocks are
equal, for example here, these two blocks
那么它们的密文一定也是一样的
happen to be equal, then necessarily the
resulting ciphertext is also going to be equal.
所以攻击者只看密文，即使他不知道
So an attacker who looks at the
ciphertext, even though he might not know
明文是写得是什么，我们知道这两个分组是一样的
what's actually written in these blocks,
we'll know that these two blocks are
因此，攻击者可以学到关于明文的一些信息
equal. And as a result, he learned
something about the plaintext that he
而这是不应该的。如果你对这个抽象还不清楚
shouldn't have learned. And if this isn't
clear enough for you abstractly, the best
最好的解释方法是用图像，就是这个家伙
to explain this is using a picture. And so
here's this guy here that, you know, has
有着深黑色头发。当我们加密时
this really dark black hair. And when we
encrypt. This image, this bitmap image
使用电子密码本加密这个位图图像
大家可以看到他的头发，包含了很多1
using the electronic code book mode. You
see that his hair, that contains lots of
总是使用同一种加密，所以它的轮廓
ones. Basically always gets encrypted the
same way, so that his silhouette,
是完全可见的，即使是在密文数据里
actually, is completely visible, even in
the encrypted data. Okay, so this is a
这时一个很好的例子，显示了电子密码本
nice example of how the electronic code
book mode can actually leak information
会泄漏给攻击者一些明文信息
about the plaintext that could tell
something to the attacker. So the question
那么问题是如何正确地使用分组密码来加密长明文
is, how to correctly use block ciphers to
encrypt long messages. And so, I just
我想简单提醒一下大家我们的目的
want to briefly remind you of the notion
we're trying to achieve, which is
即为使用一次性密钥的语义安全
basically semantic security using a one
time key. So the adversary outputs two
攻击者输出两个明文m0和m1，他获得m0的加密结果
messages, m0 and m1, and then he gets
either the encryption of m0 or the
或是m1的加密结果，这是两个不同的实验
encryption of m1, these are two different
experiments. And then our goal is to say
我们的目标是让攻击者无法区分这两个实验
that the adversary can't distinguish
between these two experiments. So you
你无法区分m0的加密和m1的加密
can't distinguish the encryption of m0
from the encryption of m1. And the reason
我们之所以叫它一次性密钥的安全，是因为
这个密钥只使用一次，只加密一个明文
we call this security for a one time key
is that the key is only used to encrypt a
因此，攻击者只能看到一个用这个密钥加密的密文
single message. And as a result, the
adversary will ever only see one ciphertext
好，那么首先我们想证明
encrypted using this key. Okay, so
the first thing we want to show is that in
事实上刚才的电子密码本
fact the mode we just looked at,
electronic code book, in fact, is not
不是语义安全的。这是正确的，只要
加密的内容超过一个分组
semantically secure. And this is true as
long as you're encrypting more than one
这是一个例子。假设我们用分组密码加密了两个分组
block. So here's an example. Suppose we
encrypt two blocks using a block cipher.
我告诉大家，事实上电子密码本是不安全的
Let me show you that in fact electronic
code book will not be secure. So here's
这么做：我们是攻击者，输出两个明文m0和m1
what we would do. So we're the adversary.
So we would output two messages, m0 and
在其中一个明文里，所有分组不同
而在另一明文里，所有分组相同
m1, where, in one message, the blocks are
distinct, and in the other message, the
这两个分组相等
blocks are the same. The two blocks are
equal to one another. Well, so what is the
挑战者怎么办？他要加密m0或m1
challenger gonna do? The challenger's
going to encrypt either m0 or m1.
两种情况我们都得到两个分组
那么密文包含了两个分组
Either way we are gonna get two blocks
back. So the ciphertext actually contains two
第一个分组是单词"Hello"的加密
blocks. The first block is going to be an
encryption of the word "Hello" and the
第二个分组是"Hello"或"World"的加密
second block is gonna be either an
encryption of the word "Hello" or the word
如果这两个密文分组一样，那么攻击者知道
"World". And if the two ciphertext blocks
are the same then the adversary knows that
他收到的是信息"Hello Hello"的加密
he received an encryption of the message
"Hello Hello" and as a difference he knows
如果不一样，他知道他收到的是
"Hello World"的加密，好吧？
that he received encryption of the
message "Hello World". Okay? So, he just
所以，攻击者遵循一个简单的策略
大家想一想，可以算出他的优势是多少
follows a simple strategy here. And if you
think about it for a second, you'll see
那么，优势是多少？
what his advantage is. So, what is the
advantage? Well, this adversary when he
这个攻击者总是输出0，当他接收到m1的加密
received an encryption of the message
m1 he will always output 0.
他总是输出1，当他接收到m0的加密
and when he receives an encryption of
the message m0 it will always output 1.
因此优势为1
And because of that the advantage,
basically, is 1, which means that the
意味着这个加密机制是不安全的
这再次说明了
scheme is not secure, which again shows you
the electronic code book is not
电子密码本不是语义安全的，永远不应
被用来加密长于一个分组的信息
semantically secure and should never ever
be used to encrypt messages that are more
那么，我们该怎么办？这有个简单例子
than one block long. So, what should we
do? Well, so here's a simple example. What
我们可以使用一个确定的计数器模式
we could do is we could use what's called
a deterministic counter mode. So in a
在确定的计数器模式下，我们由分组密码
构建一个流密码
deterministic counter mode, basically we
build a stream cipher out of the block
假设我们有一个PRF f。我说PRF时
大家应该可以想到AES
cipher. So suppose we have a PRF, F. So
again you should think of AES when I say
AES是一个安全的PRF
that. So AES is also a secure PRF. And
what we'll do is, basically, we'll evaluate
我们计算AES在点0处的值，在点1处的值
在点2，一直到点L
AES at the point zero, at the point one,
at the point two, up to the point L. This
这会产生一个伪随机密码本
我会把它和所有明文分组进行异或
will generate a pseudo random pad. And I
will XOR that with all the message
得到密文作为结果
blocks and recover the ciphertext as a
result. Okay, so really this is just a
这其实是一个由PRF构造的流密码
像AES和3DES，是个简单的加密方法
stream cipher that's built out of a PRF,
like AES and triple DES, and it's a simple
我想很快地为大家证明这个安全定理
way to do encryption. I wanted to just
very quickly show you the security
事实上，我们已经在讨论使用PRG的流密码时
看到过这个安全定理
theorem. In fact, we've already seen the
security theorem when it applied to stream
我不打算把它重复一遍
ciphers using pseudo-random generators, so
I'm not going to repeat this again. I'll
我只提醒大家，对每个试图攻击
确定的计数器模式的攻击者A
just remind you that essentially for every
adversary A that's trying to attack
我们证明存在一个试图攻击PRF的攻击者B
deterministic counter mode, we prove that
there's an adversary B that's trying to
由于这个量是可忽略的，因为PRF是安全的
attack the PRF. And since this quantity is
negligible, because the PRF is secure, we
我们得到这个量也是可忽略的
obtain that this quantity is negligible.
And therefore, the adversary has
因此，这个攻击者对确定的计数器模式
只有一个可忽略的优势
negligible advantage in defeating
deterministic counter mode. And the
这个证明用图像表示很简单
proof in pictures is a really simple
proof. So I'll just show it to you one
为求完整，我只为大家再证一次
more time for completeness. So basically,
what we want to show is, when the
当攻击者有明文m0的加密时
这是m0的加密密文
adversary's given the encryption of the
message m0, here, this is the encryption
m0异或计数器的PRF值
of the message, m0. m0 XOR counter
applied to the PRF, versus in giving the
或者是m1的加密。我们想证明这两个分布
encryption of the message, m1. We wanna
argue these two distributions are
是计算上不可区分的。那么基本证明方法是
computationally indistinguishable. So the
way we do that is basically we say, well
上面这个分布，如果是真随机函数，不是PRF
the top distribution, if instead of a PRF,
we use a truly random function, namely
这里f是一个真随机函数，那么由于PRF的性质
here f is a truly random function, then
the adversary, because of the property of
攻击者不能区分两个实验
the PRF, the adversary cannot distinguish
these two experiments, right. A PRF is
一个PRF无法和一个真随机函数相区分
indistinguishable from a truly random
function, therefore when we replace the PRF
所以当我们用右边的真随机函数替换左边的PRF时
on the left with a truly random function
on the right, the adversary is going to
攻击者的行为将是一样的
你无法区分这两个分布
behave the same. Basically you can't
distinguish these two distributions. But
但现在因为f是一个真随机函数
这个密码本是真的一次性密码本
now because F is a truly random function,
the pad here is a truly one time pad, and
因此攻击者无法区分m0的加密和m1的加密
therefore no adversary can distinguish an
encryption of m0 from an encryption of m1
在一次性密码本下。因此这两个分布是一样的
under the one time pad. So, again, these
two distributions are the same. In fact,
事实上，这里有一个等式。这两个分布
here there's an actual equality. These two
distributions literally are the same
就是一样的分布。类似地，当我们从一个真随机函数
distribution. And similarly again when we
go back from a truly random function here
回到一个PRF时，因为PRF是安全的，攻击者无法区分
to a PRF, because the PRF is secure, the
adversary can't distinguish these two
下面左、右这两个分布
bottom distributions, the left from the
right. And so by following these three
根据这三个等式，我们证明了这些
我们希望证明相等的东西
equalities, basically we have proven that
the things we wanted to prove equal are
实际上是计算不可区分的
actually computationally
indistinguishable. Okay, so that's a very
这是一个非常简单的证明，确定的计数器模式
事实上是安全的
simply proof to show that deterministic
counter mode is in fact secure and it's
这个证明和我们之前证明流密码的语义安全是一样的
basically the same proof as we had when we
proved that a stream cipher gives us
好，本节完结。下节我们讨论
semantic security. Okay. So that completes
this segment and in the next segment we'll
让我们能够使用一个密钥加密多个信息的模式
talk about modes that enable us to use a
key to encrypt multiple messages.